In the last video,
we talked about why
the closing process is
important in general.
We'll get more specific in
this video as we discuss
why closing is important for
clients and stakeholders.
A formal closing process is
important not only because
improper closing may
leave you on the hook for
incomplete contracts
or incomplete scope,
but also because you want
stakeholders to feel like
their needs were met.
As we mentioned earlier,
a project team's relationship
with customers,
users, vendors, and so on
can be impacted by loose ends.
If relationships are
impacted negatively,
your team's credibility
may be impacted.
Typically, stakeholders
set the goals and scope
of the project alongside
the project manager,
so a good project manager will
always want to make sure
those stakeholders are
satisfied with the quality of
deliverables and the
end product too.
So how can you make
sure that clients and
key stakeholders are happy
with the project closing?
First, you'll want to
decide if your project
warrants a small closing process
at the end of each milestone
or a formal and more
comprehensive closing
phase near the very end.
You may even decide to do
both the small closing
process at the end of
each milestone and a more
formal closing phase
at the very end.
You'll determine this
by asking yourself
if a particular
milestone is final,
meaning the milestone
will not need to be
readdressed at a later
time in the project.
If so, having a short,
formal closeout will
ensure that everyone is clear on
the outcomes of that
particular milestone.
For example, let's put this in
the context of the Project
Plant Pals website launch.
Launching the website is
an official milestone,
so having a formal close out to
the website launch
might make sense.
Yes, there will still be
ongoing updates and
maintenance to the site,
but it won't be launched again.
The launch is a one-time event.
You need to make sure you're
handing over deliverables,
putting together the
proper documentation,
and alerting all stakeholders
that you've reached
that milestone and
that that portion of the
project is now closed.
If you decide to conduct
closing processes after
each phase or milestone,
here is what that will
look like for your team.
First, you'll ensure
that the project has
satisfied the strategic goals
that it was intended to meet.
To begin, you'll want to refer to
prior documentation such
as your statement of work,
request for proposal, risk
register, and RACI chart.
You recall that these documents
were discussed in
previous sections,
so feel free to revisit
those as a refresher.
While doing so, ask yourself,
was all of the required work
in the elapsed phase done?
Were all identified
issues addressed?
Did every team member complete
their assigned tasks?
Then you'll put together closing
documentation such as
creating closeout reports,
which we'll cover in depth later.
You'll build and review
that documentation
with team members to
make sure that every aspect of
the project has been discussed.
You'll also review notes from
any retrospectives you and
your team participated in.
This way, your team members
will get a chance to
speak about the aspects
they liked or didn't like,
and they'll leave with
a sense of closure.
Next, you'll conduct
administrative closure
of the procurement process.
Close any contracts necessary,
deliver the payments to vendors,
and retrieve all
final deliverables
from contracted workers.
This is really important so
that external stakeholders and
contracted workers
can understand that
the phase or the project
is officially over.
Then you'll want to formally
recognize the completion
of the phase, if necessary.
Make sure all
stakeholders are aware
that a phase or
project is ending.
This may be as simple as
sending out an email
notifying them that
you've achieved
this milestone or may
warrant a larger meeting.
Finally, you'll complete any
necessary follow-up work.
This includes things
like gathering
final feedback and
conducting closing surveys.
This way, you'll proactively
help stakeholders with
future issues by following
up and offering support.
If ,instead of closing
after certain phases or
milestones, you've decided to
close at the very
end of your project,
your process may be a
little bit different.
Here is what that
might look like.
First, provide the
necessary training tools,
documentation, and capabilities
to use your product.
This includes things like
manuals and how-to guides,
which gives your customers and
users an understanding of how to
use your product or service
after the project is closed.
Next, ensure that the project has
satisfied its goals
and desired outcomes.
Review the project to make
sure that all tasks and
deliverables were completed
and nothing is missing.
Did you accomplish what
you set out to do?
Is the full scope
of work completed?
You'll also want to
document acceptance from
all stakeholders like
clients and sponsors.
Ensuring that you have
written proof that
stakeholders are
happy with the deliverables and
outcomes is very important.
This could be in retrospectives,
a project completion document,
or any other formal signoff.
Then review all contracts and
documentation with
your project team.
This includes things
like your SOW, RFP,
RACI chart, risk register,
and the procurement documents
that we discussed earlier.
Including your whole team
in this review process
will help you make sure
that nothing is missed.
Always document your
lessons learned
by conducting a
formal retrospective.
Include your team, any
other teams involved,
your stakeholders, and outside
vendors in this meeting.
We'll go over this in more
detail in the next video.
Finally, you can disband
and thank the project team.
The next important
step in closing
a project for the stakeholders
is impact reporting.
Impact reporting is a
presentation that's
given at the end of a project
for key stakeholders,
which typically includes
the stakeholders you
had in the initial
kick-off meeting.
The purpose of impact reporting
is to demonstrate how
the project went and discuss
the impact of your
product or service.
It's important for
the project manager
because you'll be able to
demonstrate the success of
your project on your terms and
present the work you did to
add value to the business.
In this presentation, you'll
cover how the project
landed in terms of time,
scope, and budget.
You'll state when the
new service or product
launch and discuss any
available feedback from users,
and you'll explain how
the desired outcomes
were achieved.
Now you know more about how
stakeholders and customers can
get a clear understanding
that your project is closed.
We've discussed why that's
necessary and how
your reputation and
credibility can be
affected if you don't
do extensive work to close
the project completely.
In the next video,
we'll discuss how your team
can be impacted by closing
a project properly and
improperly. I'll meet you there.